[Music]
according to the largest study risk
factors for death in human history a
poor diet
causes more death than anything
cigarettes only kill about 8 million
people a year whereas humanity's diet
kills millions more
what's the worst aspect of our diet
processed meat twinkies soda
no
the five deadliest things about our diet
are inadequate fruit intake not enough
fruit not enough whole grains not enough
vegetables too much salt and not enough
nuts and seeds
nuts should come as no surprise since
interventional trials have shown that
eating nuts improves artery function and
arterial diseases like heart disease are
among our leading killers
but that's not all nuts can do they may
also improve blood sugar control lower
cholesterol suppress inflammation reduce
oxidative stress and feed our friendly
gut flora
all nuts or just tree nuts what about
peanuts what about peanut butter about
50 of peanut consumption in the u.s is
through peanut butter but the
association between peanut butter and
mortality has not been thoroughly
evaluated
to get that granular though we can call
on the nih aarp study the largest
prospective health and diet study in
history that followed more than a half
million people since the 1990s and
nut consumption in general appeared to
protect against all-cause mortality
meaning nut eaters live on average
longer lives and specifically are less
likely to die from cancer cardiovascular
disease respiratory disease infectious
causes so maybe they help immunity as
well liver disease and kidney disease
however no such associations were found
for peanut butter so when it comes to
living longer peanut butter doesn't seem
to count
why
well we know peanut butter consumers
tend to eat more meat smoke cigarettes
and we're less likely to exercise but
the researchers controlled for all that
red meat white meat tobacco use exercise
and vegetables fruits and whole grains
so it's not like the peanut butter
eaters were just eating more white bread
sandwiches or something
the researchers didn't control for sugar
though so it's possible they could have
been eating more sugary jelly
it could also be the processing that
goes into making peanut butter the added
trends fat oil salt and sugar but
regular nuts are also often eated with
added oil sugar and salt
could it just be the peanuts themselves
i mean technically they aren't nuts so
maybe they just don't have the same
benefits but no a meta-analysis of all
such studies found the same nut-like
benefits for whole peanuts just not
peanut butter
well one thing missing from even no salt
oil-free sugar-free nut and seed butters
is intact cellular structure as i noted
and how not to diet no matter how well
we chew whole or chopped nuts some of
the nutrients remain trapped in tiny
particles that deliver a bounty of
prebiotic goodness to our friendly flora
that makes me wonder if there would have
been any difference between chunky and
smooth peanut butter
in the meanwhile there is compelling
evidence to recommend the use of nuts
preferably raw nuts over salt that are
toasted and whole or chopped nuts rather
than nut butters at least three times a
week in order to maximize our chances of
living longer and healthier lives
[Music]
you